NUEVE MESES ANTES A:middle T:50%
Mr. Tillerson.
We found something.
and I jump...
Es una roca.
That's a rock.
Look...
it must be him...
Where'd you find this?
A mile or so out...
near the Abbotts' west pasture.
Have you seen it before?
Once...
as a kid...
You find any more of this...
I want you to bring it right to me.
Understand?
Leave it there.
Get outta here.
TIERRAS DE NADIE
Matt?
- ¿Matt? - Sí, aquí estoy.
Yeah. I'm here.
¿Sacaste la hebilla del cinturón de Trevor del cajón?
Did you take Trevor's belt buckle out of my desk?
No, ¿por qué? ¿No está?
No. Why? Is it missing?
Um... let me ask you.
Dime, ¿cuánto tiempo estuvo Royal merodeando cerca de mi oficina anoche?
How long you think Royal was hanging around
- my office last night? - I don't know.
No sé. ¿Unos diez minutos?
Ten minutes. Wait.
¿Crees que se la llevó?
You think he took it?
Quizá no deberías dejar evidencia...
You know, you probably...
shouldn't leave evidence...
¡Lo sé, Matt! ¡Lo sé!
I know that, Matt! I know that!
Esa verja está muy dañada.
Gate back there was pretty busted.
That the one Luke drove through?
¿Fue la que atravesó Luke?
Yeah, I ought to send him a bill.
Sí, debo enviarle la factura.
Espera a después del funeral.
Maybe wait until after the funeral.
"The Big Rock Candy Mountain"]
ALGUACIL
The way you brought us, is that the only way up?
¿Solo se puede subir por donde nos trajiste?
Es el único camino que conozco.
It's the only way I know.
El rigor mortis ya pasó, lleva mucho aquí.
Rigor mortis come and gone,
so he's probably been here awhile.
No stink though.
Pero no huele mal.
Es un golpe serio en la garganta.
It's a serious shot to the throat.
Animal maybe?
¿Quizá fue un animal?
Grizzly, maybe a mountain lion?
¿Un oso pardo? ¿O quizá un puma?
No, he'd a been breakfast.
No, se lo hubiese desayunado.
Maybe he fell?
¿Quizá se cayó?
Onto his throat?
¿Sobre la garganta?
¿Y de dónde?
And from where?
Well...
Bueno...
no sign of Trevor,
No hay señales de Trevor ni de nadie más en ningún lado.
or... anyone else coming from anywhere.
Royal, ¿estamos en tus tierras?
Royal, this your land, where we are now?
No. It's BLM.
No, del Dpto. de Tierras. La nuestra acaba en la línea de los árboles.
Our property ends at the tree line, down by the trailhead.
¿Qué opinas?
So what do you think?
I think we got some figuring out to do, Royal.
Creo que tenemos que investigar, Royal.
¿Y Rhett?
Where's Rhett?
En el pueblo, haciendo un mandado.
Oh, in town at Taylor's. Running an errand.
Oh.
VE A LO DE TAYLOR, VIGILA A RHETT
Okay.
Bueno.
No creíste que serías una heroína hoy, ¿cierto?
Bet you didn't think you'd be a hero today, huh?
En mi opinión, lo eres.
Well, you are one in my book.
Ahora, tengo que hacer preguntas
Now...
I just have to...
para tener la información que necesitamos.
ask you a few things, make sure we got all the info
Disculpa, ¿quieres café? Acabo de hacer.
- we need... I'm good. - Sorry, did you want coffee?
I just made a pot and we also got... didn't you...?
Y también tenemos... ¿Qué hiciste?
- What did you make? - Banana bread... you want
¿Quieres pan de banana?
- some banana bread? - Yeah, you want some banana bread?
Soy alérgica.
I'm allergic to bananas.
You're allergic to bananas?
- ¿Eres alérgica a las bananas? - Sí.
- Yeah. - What happens if you eat one?
- ¿Qué pasa si te comes una? - Shock anafiláctico.
Anaphylactic shock.
Huh.
Bien, Amy, estabas caminando y hallaste a Trevor.
So, Amy.
You were on your hike, found Trevor,
Viniste, le contaste al abuelo, y él me llamó.
ran home, told your grandpa, your grandpa called me.
- ¿Lo entendí bien? - Sí, creo que sí.
Do I got that right?
Yeah, I guess so.
¿Cuándo fue la última vez que fuiste ahí?
When's the last time you hiked that trail?
Um...
Hace unos días.
- a few days ago. - She walks it all the time...
Siempre pasea por ahí.
Sorry, Per, if you don't mind I, I just have to hear it from her.
Disculpa, Per. Si no te importa, quiero que ella me lo diga.
Did you...
¿Notaste algo extraño la última vez que estuviste ahí?
notice anything out of the ordinary
when you were up there last?
¿Cómo qué cosa?
What do you mean, like what?
Huellas.
Tracks. People.
Personas, basura.
Trash.
¿Eso es extraño?
Are those "out of the ordinary"?
Sorry.
Está bien.
No.
No, no vi nada.
I didn't see anything.
Let me ask you this then.
Déjame preguntarte esto.
¿Recuerdas cuando Luke y Billy Tillerson vinieron hace unas noches?
Do you remember a few nights ago
when Luke and Billy Tillerson came by?
Sí.
Yeah.
¿Viste a Luke y a Billy?
Did you see... Luke and Billy?
They were being weird.
Se portaron raro.
They were drunk.
- Estaban ebrios. - Sí.
Yeah.
And, um...
Y...
who else was at the house then, you remember?
¿recuerdas quién más estaba en la casa?
Uh... my dad.
Mi papá.
And my grandma was asleep, but then she came down to get me.
Y mi abuela estaba dormida, pero luego bajó a buscarme.
Was your grandpa here, too?
¿Tu abuelo también estaba?
Sí. Estaba acostado, era tarde.
Yeah.
He was in bed. It was late.
Asleep?
¿Dormido?
Sí. Caigo rendido como a las 9:30.
Yeah, I'm pretty much dead at30.
Man could sleep through a tornado.
Podría dormir durante un tornado.
What about your Uncle Rhett?
¿Y tu tío Rhett? ¿Estaba aquí?
Was he here?
No.
No, he wasn't here.
No, no estaba aquí.
Do you know where he was?
¿Sabes dónde estaba?
No.
I don't know where he was.
No sé dónde estaba.
Okay.
Está bien.
Bueno, muchas gracias.
Well, thanks so much.
Amy, quizá puedas convencer a tu papá
I'll tell you, Amy, I think you could probably convince your dad
para que te deje divertirte hoy.
to let you skip chores today, do something fun.
Can we watch a movie with Grandma?
¿Vemos una película con la abuela?
- Por mí está bien. - Claro, nena.
- Fine by me. - Sure, honey.
Oye, ¿sabes algo?
Hey, um, you know...
No quería decirlo delante de Amy,
I didn't want to...
say it with Amy around, but, um...
pero,
Rhett estaba con una chica esa noche.
Rhett was with a girl that night.
Oh. Do you know who?
¿Sabes quién era?
Uh... no.
No.
I don't know.
No lo sé.
Okay.
All right.
Está bien. Es bueno saberlo.
Well, good to know.
- ¿Sabe sobre el cadáver? - ¿Por qué?
Does he know about the body?
Why?
Solo preguntaba.
Just wondering.
No hemos podido localizarlo.
We haven't been able to reach him.
Royal, you mind walking to my truck?
Roy, ¿puedes acompañarme al auto?
Claro que sí.
No, sure thing.
Gracias por avisarnos.
Well, thanks for calling it in.
¿Por qué no lo haría?
Yeah, why wouldn't I?
Claro.
Right.
Pasó algo muy curioso.
You know, funniest thing happened.
Recibimos otras 12 llamadas
We got 12 different calls from folks saying
y dijeron que la montaña había desaparecido.
they saw that mountain right there disappear in plain sight.
- ¿En serio? - Qué locura, ¿verdad?
No, you serious?
- Crazy, right? - Yeah.
Sí.
Me recordó cuando toda esa gente dijo
Reminded me of when there were all those folks talking
about a flying saucer up in Montana, you remember that?
haber visto un platillo en Montana, ¿lo recuerdas?
No.
You take anything out of my office?
¿Te llevaste algo de mi oficina?
What?
¿Qué?
¿Tomaste algo de mi oficina?
Did you take something from my office?
- When, last night? - Last night.
- ¿Anoche? - Sí.
No.
¿Estás seguro?
- You sure about that? - Yeah.
Sí.
Why, you missing something?
¿Por qué? ¿Falta algo?
Yeah.
Sí.
Oh.
Well, I hope you find it.
Espero que lo encuentres.
Okay.
Nos vemos, Royal.
I'll be seeing you, Royal.
Bien.
Yep.
Matt, you there?
Matt, ¿estás ahí?
Encontré a Rhett.
- Found Rhett. - I need you
Pregúntale qué hizo tras la pelea con Trevor.
to go ask him what he did after the fight with Trevor.
Esto es importante. No lo dejes contestar el teléfono.
But look, this is important: don't let him
answer his phone, okay?
He doesn't know about the body.
No sabe sobre el cadáver.
- Llama a tu hermano. - Sí.
- Call your brother. - I'm on it.
Elije entrar.
Choose enter.
Cancélala.
Cancel.
Cancélala otra vez.
Cancel again.
And that's how you open an account.
Así se abre una cuenta.
Hey, Rhett!
¡Oye, Rhett!
BISON VALLEY BANCO DE WYOMING
- Hey. - Hey.
- Hola. - Hola.
¿Cómo están? Rhett, ¿podemos hablar?
Wow. Hey, you two.
Rhett, can we chat?
Uh...
¿Estás bien?
- Are you okay? - Yeah, I'm fine.
Sí, estoy bien.
I, uh...
Espera. Mi hermano ha intentado...
Matt, hold on a sec. My brother's been trying...
Te pediré que no contestes el teléfono.
Rhett, I'm gonna ask that you don't answer that telephone.
- ¿Por qué? - ¿Qué pasa?
- What? Why? - What's going on?
Talk to me for one sec.
Háblame, pero no contestes eso.
Don't answer that phone, all right?
- Puede usarlo. - Tengo...
- The guy can use his phone. - No, I got this. It's fine.
Solo una cosa.
- Matt... - I just got to ask him one thing.
Mi hermano...
I'm sorry, my brother's been trying to get me...
¿Qué hiciste tras pelear con Trevor?
Where'd you go after the fight with Trevor?
¿Qué? ¿Por qué?
What? Why?
Where were you after the fight with Trevor?
¿Dónde estabas después de la pelea con Trevor?
No contestes el teléfono.
Don't answer that phone.
Disculpe, tengo que...
I'm sorry, I got to...
- Hola. - Hallaron a Trevor.
- Hey. - They found Trevor.
Debes decir que estabas con una chica esa noche.
- Rhett. - You got to tell them
you were with a girl that night.
¿Rhett?
Rhett?
Rhett, I'm not gonna ask you again.
Rhett, no lo preguntaré de nuevo.
¿A dónde fuiste después de la pelea con Trevor?
Where'd you go after you got into a fight with Trevor?
- Estaba con una chica. - ¿Estabas con una chica?
I was with a girl.
You were with a girl?
- Sí. - ¿Con quién?
Yeah.
Who were you with?
Rhett.
Rhett?
Estaba conmigo.
He was with me.
Rhett, is that true?
Rhett, ¿es cierto?
Sí.
Yeah.
All right.
Está bien.
Bueno, gracias.
Well, thanks.
No hay más preguntas.
That's all I had for you.
Estás trabajando, cariño.
You're on the clock here, honey.
Billy!
¡Billy!
Por favor, ¿puedes callarte?
Please, can you quit it?
Sorry.
Disculpa.
"Angel of the Morning"]
Hice un sándwich extra.
I made an extra sandwich.
It's for you.
Es para ti.
can't bind your heart...
¿Qué?
What?
¡Santo cielo!
Jesus Christ.
Me asustaste.
You scared me.
Why are you out here?
¿Por qué estás aquí?
Te estaba buscando.
I was looking for you.
Encontraron un cadáver en la ladera.
They found a body on the hillside there.
Our neighbor.
Nuestro vecino.
Dios mío.
God.
¿Sabes algo al respecto?
Do you know anything about that?
No.
¿Segura?
You sure?
Yeah.
Sí.
Is that hillside west pasture?
¿Fue en el pastizal de la colina?
¿Por qué?
Why?
Ahí está mi campamento.
My camp's west pasture.
It is.
Así es.
Okay.
Bueno.
¿Necesitas algo de nosotros?
Is there anything you need from us?
¿Me das una foto de tu esposa?
How about a picture of your wife?
¿Qué?
What?
Bueno, he estado por aquí. Quizá la haya visto.
Well, I've been all around this area.
Maybe I've seen her.
Pasan cosas raras.
Stranger things happen.
Sé qué le hace el oro al alma de los hombres.
Diga.
Hello?
Hola, Todd.
Hi, Todd.
Disculpa, hoy es un mal día para...
Sorry, today is a bad day to...
¿Tan pronto?
Why that soon?
All right.
Veré qué puedo hacer.
I'll see what I can do.
Está bien, adiós.
Okay. Bye.
Voy por un trago. ¿Quieres algo?
I'm gonna grab a drink. You want something?
¿Qué fue eso? ¿Sobre Trevor?
What was that? About Trevor?
No. Lawyer calling about the Tillerson land situation.
El abogado llamó por lo de la tierra de Tillerson.
¿Estás bien?
You doing all right?
He didn't have to call that in right away.
No tenía que denunciarlo de inmediato.
Yes, he absolutely did.
Sí, claro que sí.
¿Qué más querías que hiciera?
What else would you have him do?
You want to explain to your daughter
¿Quieres explicarle a tu hija...?
why her family isn't reporting...
¿Por qué puso el cadáver ahí en primer lugar?
Why the hell did he put the body up there
in the first place?
- Dijo que no había sido él. - ¿Cómo llegó ahí?
He said he didn't.
Then how'd it get there?
County assessor set the west pasture hearing
El tasador fijó la audiencia de los pastizales para fin de mes.
for the end of the month.
Eso no puede ser.
Yeah, well, that can't happen.
So what do you want to do?
¿Qué quieres hacer?
Le haré una visita.
I'll pay him a visit.
Si no fuiste tú, ¿cómo llegó ese cadáver ahí?
If, uh, you didn't do it,
then how did that body get up there?
Trust me, I wish I knew.
Quisiera saberlo, créeme.
¿Crees que esa chica tuvo algo que ver?
You think that girl had something to do with it?
Es decir,
I mean, she saw you that night, right?
te vio esa noche, ¿cierto? Tuvo que ser ella.
It'd have to be her.
No, no lo creo.
Yeah, I don't, I don't think so.
¿Por qué no?
Why not?
- Royal. - ¿Qué?
- Royal. - What?
Por favor, no me obligues a sacarte esto.
Please don't make me draw this out of you.
Estoy cansada de presionarte.
I'm-I'm tired of pushing you.
No puedo decirte lo que no sé, Ceci.
I can't tell you what I don't know, Ceci.
No es el mismo silencio que he soportado por 30 años.
This-this is not the same kind of quiet
that I've put up with for 30 years.
No imaginas lo que hice por nuestros chicos esa noche.
Okay, you have no idea what I did for our boys that night.
No estoy hablando de eso. Esto es diferente.
I'm not talking about that. T-This is different.
This is something more.
Esto es otra cosa.
I see it. The boys see it.
Los chicos y yo lo vemos.
No puedo explicar muchas cosas.
Okay, there's a lot I can't explain.
- ¡Inténtalo! - Eso hago. Todo lo que hago es intentarlo.
- Well, try! - I am trying.
That's all I do, is try!
Y si confiaras en mí...
And if you'd just trust me...
¡Te he apoyado siempre!
I have stood by you at every turn!
En las heridas, en las sequías, en los incendios,
Every single injury, every drought, every fire,
cada vez que no podías pagar las cuentas.
every time you fucking couldn't pay the goddamn bills.
Con lo de Rebecca, con esto. Y, carajo, lo logramos.
Through Rebecca. Through this.
And-and, holy shit, we made it, we stuck together,
Seguimos juntos porque era necesario.
because we had to.
And all a sudden, you're telling me
¿De repente me dices que quieres hacerlo solo?
you want to go it alone?
¿Sabes lo que se siente?
Do you know what that feels like?
LÍNEA POLICIAL - NO CRUZAR
- Gracias. - Sí.
- Thank you. - Yep.
Hola, María. ¿Tienes un minuto?
Hi, Maria. You got a minute?
Claro. Descansaré en 10 minutos.
Sure. I'm on a break in ten.
¿Y si descansas ahora?
How about you take your break now?
¿Cuánto llevas en el banco?
How long you been working at the bank?
Unas semanas.
A few weeks.
- ¿Te gusta? - Está bien.
- You like it? - It's all right.
You were with Rhett the night Trevor disappeared,
¿Estuviste con Rhett la noche que Trevor desapareció?
is that right?
Yeah.
Sí.
- ¿Estudiaste con Rhett? - En secundaria.
You go to school with Rhett?
- High school. - High school.
Secundaria.
¿Rhett te llevó a casa esa noche?
So did Rhett drive you home that night?
Yeah.
Sí.
¿A qué hora?
What time was that?
A la 1:00 o 1:30.
00,- 30.
Great.
Estupendo.
Now, if I call your parents, can they confirm that?
Si llamo a tus padres, ¿podrán confirmarlo?
Well, they were asleep when I got home,
Estaban dormidos cuando llegué. Dudo que puedan confirmarlo.
so I doubt they can.
Maria, Trevor Tillerson was found this morning
María,
a Trevor Tillerson lo encontraron cerca del Rancho Abbott.
near the Abbotts' ranch.
Está muerto.
He's dead.
Look, it's completely normal to want to protect a friend.
Es muy normal que quieras proteger a un amigo.
Pero esto es un posible homicidio.
But this is likely a homicide.
And believe me when I tell you, the best thing for anyone to do
Y créeme cuando te digo que lo mejor
que alguien puede hacer cuando le preguntan por un homicidio
when being questioned in conjunction with a homicide
es decir la verdad.
is to tell the truth.
Porque cuando no dices la verdad,
'Cause when you don't tell the truth,
even for what can seem like the right reasons, well,
incluso cuando parezca ser por la razón correcta,
bueno,
there are really bad consequences.
hay pésimas consecuencias.
No nueve de cada diez,
Not nine times out of ten.
sino diez de diez.
Ten times out of ten.
You understand what I'm telling you?
¿Entiendes lo que te estoy diciendo?
Sí.
Yeah.
So...
Entonces...
was there anyone else behind the bar
¿Había alguien más detrás del bar cuando Rhett y Trevor se pelearon?
when Rhett and Trevor got in the fight?
¿PODEMOS HABLAR? ESTARÁ BIEN
LO LAMENTO POR FAVOR, LLÁMAME
Hello?
Diga.
Empecemos con lo que pasó después de la pelea con Trevor.
Let's start with
what happened after the fight with Trevor.
I grabbed Perry and we left.
Agarré a Perry y nos fuimos.
Did you drive home in your truck or Rhett's truck?
¿En tu camioneta o en la de Rhett?
En la de Rhett.
Rhett's.
Me dejó. Supongo que salió otra vez.
He dropped me off, and I guess he went back out.
You know where?
¿Sabes a dónde?
To see Maria, I think.
A ver a María, creo.
To see Maria, yeah.
A ver a María, sí.
¿Qué hicieron María y tú?
And what'd you and Maria do?
Look, I don't really remember...
Realmente no recuerdo...
María me confesó que había mentido.
Maria confessed to me that she lied.
Que ustedes no salieron esa noche.
That you guys didn't go back out that night.
¿Sabes por qué mentiría sobre eso?
Do you know why she would lie about that?
I-I don't know why she'd lie to you.
No sé por qué te mentiría.
Ask Rhett.
- Pregúntale a Rhett. - ¿Qué cosa?
- Ask Rhett what? - What happened.
Lo que sucedió.
Me dijo qué sucedió.
He told me what happened.
¿Hay algo de Perry que no me estás diciendo?
Is there something you're not telling me about Perry?
¿Y de tu papá?
What about your dad?
Do you think your dad's hiding something from me?
¿Crees que tu papá me oculta algo?
Si no estuviste con María, ¿dónde estabas?
If you weren't with Maria, then where were you?
With Perry?
¿Con Perry?
Sé que es tu hermano, pero sé listo,
I know he's your brother, but be smart.
piensa en tu carrera en el rodeo.
Think about that rodeo career.
Look...
Supuse que Rhett había dicho la verdad.
I assume Rhett was telling me the truth.
Maria said the last person she saw in that parking lot
María dijo que la última persona que vio en el estacionamiento fuiste tú.
was you.
Perry, you and I been through a lot.
Perry, tú y yo hemos pasado muchas cosas.
No quiero arrastrarte junto a tu familia a otra tragedia,
Last thing I want to do is drag you and your family
through another tragedy.
Especially Amy. This is important, okay?
y menos a Amy.
Es importante, ¿bien?
Do you know where Rhett went after you got home?
¿Sabes a dónde fue Rhett después de que llegaste a casa?
No. No lo sé.
No. I don't know.
Dijiste que estabas con una chica.
You told Matt you were with a girl.
Sí.
Yes.
Pero no fue así. ¿Dónde estabas?
But you weren't, so where were you?
Maria says she doesn't know.
María dijo que no sabe.
- Tu hermano dice que no sabe. - ¿Perry dijo eso?
Your brother says he doesn't know.
That's what Perry said?
Verificó lo que me dijo María.
He verified exactly what Maria told me.
Nadie sabe dónde estuviste durante dos horas muy importantes.
Nobody knows where you were
for two very important hours, Rhett.
La sangre de tu hermano estaba en la hebilla de Trevor, no la tuya.
Your brother's blood
was on Trevor's belt buckle, not yours.
Perry fue el último al que vieron con Trevor, no a ti.
Perry was the last one seen with Trevor, not you.
Te lo preguntaré por última vez.
So I'll ask you one last time.
¿Hay algo que quieras decirme sobre tu hermano?
Is there something you want to tell me about your brother?
All right, boys! Let's get you home.
Bien, chicos, vámonos a casa.
¿Qué pasó?
- What happened? - We're okay.
- Estamos bien. - ¿Qué diablos dijiste de mí?
- What the fuck did you say about me? - What?
¿Qué? Nada. ¿Por qué?
- Nothing. Why? - Rhett, let's do this at home.
Rhett, hablemos en casa.
Piensa bien antes de lanzarme a los leones, Per, ¿sí?
Think twice before you throw me under the bus, Per.
All right?
Si vas a culpar a tu hermano...
I swear to God, if you're throwing this
- towards your brother... - Course I'm not. I'm...
Claro que no.
What am I supposed to do?
¿Qué debo hacer?
¿Quieres que vuelva y confiese?
Dad, you want me to go back in there and confess?
I want you to keep your fucking mouth shut.
Quiero que te calles.
I want you to buck up and be smart for once.
Quiero que seas fuerte y listo, para variar.
¡Maldita sea!
Goddamn it.
What do you need me to do?
¿Qué necesitas que haga?
I don't know.
No sé.
¿Retroceder el tiempo?
Turn back time?
Billy.
¿Por qué no pediste que investigaran antes?
How could you not push them to investigate sooner?
Quiero llorar a mi hijo sin que me jodas, Patricia.
I'd like to mourn my son
without you breaking my balls, Patricia.
Tenía cinco días desaparecido.
Wayne, he was missing for five days.
Si te importaba tanto, no debiste irte.
Well, if you cared so much, you should've stuck around.
Oh, please, don't you dare.
Por favor, no te atrevas.
No me permitiste llevármelo.
You're the one who wouldn't let me take them with me.
Because this is their home.
Porque esta es su casa.
Wyoming es su hogar.
Wyoming is their home.
Not Aspen.
No Aspen.
¡Wyoming!
Wyoming!
Dios mío.
Jesus.
Oh...
Fuck.
Carajo.
¿Has pensando en un funeral?
Have you thought about a funeral?
Algo pequeño, no quiero hablar con hipócritas.
Something small. I don't want to be speaking
to a bunch of glad-handers.
Luke cree que los chicos Abbott lo mataron.
Luke thinks the Abbott boys killed him.
You think that's true?
¿Crees que sea verdad?
Ocultan algo.
They're hiding something.
Siempre lo hacen.
Always have.
¿Algo sobre Trevor?
Something about Trevor?
About the land.
Sobre la tierra.
Será mía.
It'll be mine.
El tasador se está encargando.
County assessor's got it covered.
Oh, my God,
Oh, santo cielo.
Es esa estupidez de los pastizales occidentales.
if this is that west pasture nonsense Luke told me about...
No es una estupidez, son valiosos.
It's not nonsense, it's valuable.
And if you're still concerned with your lousy 10% stake...
Y si aún te preocupa tu maldita participación del 10 %...
'Cause you are certi-fucking-fiably insane.
¡Hazme el favor de olvidar tus jodidas supersticiones!
No! Do us all a favor, cut the superstitious bullshit!
I got news for you, there's more, there's more,
Hay más en juego que dinero.
there's more than money
at play here, toots.
Pelear unas tontas hectáreas es perder el tiempo.
Going after a few lousy acres is a waste of everyone's time.
Stop!
¡Basta!
Toma esa roca.
Pick up that rock.
¿Qué es?
What is it?
Eso, Patty,
That, Patty...
es lo que todos hemos estado buscando.
is what we've all been looking for.
¿A qué te refieres? ¿Es valiosa?
What do you mean? It's valuable?
Cuán a menudo de noche
Cuando el cielo brilla
Cuando la luz De las estrellas titilantes
Me paro allí extasiado
Y pregunto mientras contemplo
Si su gloria supera
La nuestra
Hay algo allá afuera.
There's something out there.
Está bien.
All right.
You know what?
¿Sabes algo?
Vamos a hacer lo siguiente.
Here's how this is gonna work.
I'm gonna plan this funeral,
Voy a planificar el funeral
y luego averiguaré quién asesinó a mi hijo.
and then I'm gonna find out who murdered my son.
Después me aseguraré de que Luke salve el rancho
And then I'm gonna make sure Luke saves this ranch
mientras tú enloqueces y mueres.
while you slowly lose your mind and die.
Es bueno tener una lista.
It's good to have a list.
Still got a fine nutcracker, Patty.
Todavía sabes cómo fastidiar, Patty.
TASADOR
Yeah?
- ¿Sí? - Hola. ¿Karl Cleaver?
Hi, there. Karl Cleaver?
Yeah, our lawyer mentioned
Habló del problema Tillerson con nuestro abogado.
that you chatted about the Tillerson dispute.
I was already in town, so I thought I'd just...
Ya estaba en el pueblo...
- Claro, adelante, Roy. - Gracias.
Oh, right, right, right, come on in, Roy-boy.
Thank you.
¿Cómo han sido los primeros meses?
How's the first few months been?
Shelley no te hace trabajar mucho, ¿o sí?
- Shelley's not riding you too hard, is he? - Ha!
- ¿El suave Shelley? - Sí.
Old Softy Shelley?
Man's as weak as a whisker.
Es blando como un bigote.
¿En qué puedo ayudarte?
So, what can I do you for?
Quiero solucionar el problema de los pastizales.
Well, I was hoping we could clear up
this west pasture issue.
Esta tierra ha sido de mi familia...
You know, that land's belonged to my family for over...
La audiencia será a fin de mes.
Well, the hearing will be at the end of the month.
Veamos qué sucede.
We'll just have to see how it goes.
Mm-hmm.
Karl, tú y yo sabemos que no piden algo legítimo.
Karl, you and I both know that that claim's not legit.
- The Tillersons... - Hearing will be end of the month.
- Los Tillerson... - La audiencia será a fin de mes.
Huh.
Bien. Supe que hubo una gran conmoción en el rancho.
So, I heard you had quite some commotion
up at the ranch there.
Vecinos molestos, cadáveres.
Angry neighbors, dead bodies.
- ¿De dónde eres? - Nací y me crié en Texas.
Where you from, Karl?
Texas, born and bred.
- ¿Qué opinas de Wyoming? - Bueno, te diré...
What you think of Wyoming?
Well, I'll tell you...
No sé por qué toleran las rarezas que pasan por aquí.
I don't know why you folks
put up with all the oddities coming through here.
Y'all got buffalo and immigrants and Indians running around.
Tienen búfalos, inmigrantes, indios por todos lados.
Alguien me dijo que... ¿quién fue?
Heck, somebody told me that, um...
Kanye West y Kimmie Kardashian compran muchos pueblos.
was it... Kanye West and Kimmie Kardashian,
they're buying up whole towns.
Bueno, vive y deja vivir.
Yeah, well, live and let live.
No debemos meternos en los asuntos de los demás,
You know, we stay out of people's business around here
if you catch my drift, which is why...
- por lo que... - Se está yendo al diablo.
Hell in a handbasket, you ask me.
Why I wanted to chat about this west pasture.
Quería hablar sobre el pastizal.
Put down the Fritos, pal.
Deja los Fritos, amigo.
Escúchame bien, gordo tragón.
Now you listen to me, you slack-jawed tub of guts,
I know the Tillersons are paying you off,
Los Tillerson te pagaron.
Pero óyeme cuando digo que mis pastizales son míos.
but hear me when I say my west pasture
is my west pasture, and if you don't call off that hearing,
Y si no cancelas la audiencia,
I might just have to show you a nice big hole in the earth
te voy a presentar un hoyo en la tierra al que no querrás conocer.
that you do not want to be acquainted with.
'Cause guess what you're not gonna find in that hole, Karl.
¿Porque adivina qué no encontrarás en ese agujero, Karl?
¿Fritos?
- Fritos? - There are no Fritos in that hole, Karl.
No hay Fritos en ese agujero, Karl.
So munch up while you can, big boy,
Come mientras puedas, grandote, porque tengo planes para ti.
'cause I got plans for you.
Shelley, bonito sombrero.
Shelley. Nice hat.
- Joy, this is Trevor's... - Oh, no, we know each other.
Joy, es la madre de Trevor...
Nos conocemos desde tus inicios.
From when you started.
Con Burt.
Under Burt.
Me alegra que lo lograras.
I'm glad you finally made it.
Bienvenida.
Welcome back.
I'm sorry for your loss.
Lamento tu pérdida.
Sé que no puede ser fácil.
I know this can't be easy.
Será más fácil cuando arresten a alguien.
It'll be a lot easier when you all make an arrest.
Well, why don't I, um, get started?
Bueno, es mejor que comience.
No te culpo por sentirte frustrada. Hacemos lo que podemos.
I don't blame you for being frustrated.
We're doing our best.
Lo sé.
I know that.
Tenemos muchas ganas de seguir nuestras vidas.
No, we're all just so eager to move on.
Hice que Gary acelerara todo para sepultar a Trevor el viernes.
I had Gary speed things up here so we could bury Trevor Friday.
Espero que vayas.
I hope you'll come.
Podrías conseguir algunos votos.
Hell, you might even snag a few votes.
Lo lamento, Gary, has sido muy paciente.
I'm sorry.
Gary, you've been so patient.
Muy bien.
All right, well...
No puedes presenciar el informe forense.
Hold on, Ms. Tillerson, you can't be in here
for the coroner's report, it's against the law.
Es ilegal.
Well, can you make an exception?
¿Puedes hacer una excepción? Prefiero estar aquí.
I'd really rather be here.
Why is that?
¿Y por qué?
It took five days to find my son's body,
Tardaron cinco días en encontrar el cadáver de mi hijo.
Cuatro días para que tu agencia mostrara algún interés,
four days for your office to even show any concern,
y es tu primer homicidio.
and you've never handled a murder,
No confío en que sepas lo que haces.
so I don't actually trust that you know what you're doing.
There's a lot of folks around here that feel the same.
Muchos aquí piensan igual.
Y se niegan a votar por alguien como tú.
They're all pretty reticent to vote for someone like you,
Después de todo esto, no puedo culparlos.
and after all this, well, I can't say I blame them.
Si quieres ganar la elección,
If you want to win that election, you'd do well
recuerda a quiénes sirves.
to remember who it is you serve.
Sirvo a la gente del condado de Amelia.
I serve the people of Amelia County.
Lo hago defendiendo la ley, y como dije...
And I do that by upholding the law, and like I said...
Well.
Bueno...
Please be quick.
Por favor, no tardes.
Murió de traumatismo en la tráquea.
Died from blunt force trauma to his windpipe.
La gran pregunta es por qué estaba tan limpio.
The big question we ran into is how come it's so clean?
¿Qué significa?
- Clean how? - Aside for some metal lacerations
Aparte de las laceraciones de metal, no hay residuos,
on his torso, there's no residue, no drag marks, nothing.
ni raspones, nada.
Y me parece anormal porque apareció en una montaña.
For showing up on a mountain, that's what I'd call an anomaly.
But here's the hardest part:
Pero esto es lo más difícil.
Llevaba muerto menos de diez horas cuando lo hallaron.
He was dead less than ten hours from when he was found.
Are you sure?
¿Estás seguro?
Hice tres análisis. Nos sorprendió.
Ran it three times. Surprised us, too.
¿Última vez que lo vieron?
When was he last seen?
Eight days ago.
Hace ocho días.
"Tiempo de lamentarse, y tiempo de bailar,
A time to mourn and a time to dance.
tiempo de lanzar piedras, y tiempo de recoger piedras,
A time to scatter stones
and a time to gather stones together.
A time to embrace and a time to...
tiempo de abrazar, y tiempo de...".
No le dijeron que parara.
Nobody told you to stop.
"Y un momento para no aceptarlo.
and a time to refrain from embracing.
A time to get and a time to lose.
Tiempo de buscar, y tiempo de dar por perdido,
tiempo de guardar, y tiempo de desechar,
A time to keep and a time to cast away.
tiempo de romper, y tiempo de coser.
A time to rend and a time to sow.
Tiempo de callar, y tiempo de hablar".
A time to keep silence and a time to speak.
Fue Perry.
It was Perry.
Hermosa canción.
Beautiful singing.
Who are you?
- ¿Quién eres? - Soy Autumn.
I'm Autumn.
Where's Rose?
- ¿Dónde está Rose? - Juega con Mac.
Playing with Matt.
Pretty ballsy showing up here.
Qué descaro que hayan venido. Quizá digan la verdad.
Maybe they're telling the truth?
Either that or Royal Abbott is a damn good con man.
Es eso, o Royal Abbott es un excelente estafador.
Thank you so much for coming.
Muchas gracias por venir. Lo sé, es trágico.
I know, it is tragic.
Hola, ¿podemos hablar?
Hey, can we talk?
No debí permitirte que dijeras que estabas conmigo.
I never should have let you say that you were with me.
I-I froze. I'm sorry.
Me paralicé, lo lamento.
María, no fui yo, te lo juro.
Maria, this isn't me.
- I promise. - Look, I like you.
Me gustas.
Pero no quiero ser parte de lo que haya hecho tu familia.
But whatever you're wrapped up in with your family,
I don't want any part of it.
Lo lamento, no puedo.
I'm sorry, I just can't.
Vaya servicio.
Quite a service.
Sí, vaya familia.
Yeah, quite a family.
¿Hallaste lo que buscabas?
You find what you were looking for?
No, actually.
A decir verdad, no.
Mm.
Well, retrace your steps.
Retoma tus pasos.
Ese es el asunto.
That's just the thing.
No hay pasos que retomar.
It doesn't feel like there's any steps to retrace.
Todo está desapareciendo. ¿Sabes?
Everything's just kind of disappearing.
- Hmm. - You know?
Yeah, it's a crazy world.
Sí, el mundo está loco.
Es una época extraña. ¿Qué se puede hacer?
Strange times. What can you do?
Lo mismo de siempre.
Same as I've always done.
Ser paciente, seguir buscando, ya aparecerá algo.
- Be patient, keep looking. - Mm.
Something will show up.
El mundo no está tan loco.
World is not that crazy.
You ever wonder if the world's not what you think it is?
¿Te has preguntado si el mundo no es lo que piensas?
¿De qué hablas?
What are you talking about?
No hay leyes.
No law, no order.
No hay orden.
Just chaos all the way down.
Solo caos en todos lados.
Mira alrededor.
Heck, look around.
Acabamos de sepultar a un hombre,
We just put a man into the earth,
y lo único que hacen es beber como tontos.
and it's all folks can do but drink themselves silly...
Evitan la oscuridad,
fending off the dark.
Fending off the end.
evitan el final.
Voy a ensuciar la porcelana.
I'm gonna hit the jakes.
BAÑOS
¿Sra. Abbott? Soy Karl P. Cleaver, tasador del condado.
Mrs. Abbott? Karl P. Cleaver, county assessor.
Su esposo me visitó esta semana.
Your husband paid me a visit this week.
Yo tenía la intención de visitarlo.
Yes, well, I've been meaning to pay you a visit myself.
No es necesario. Su audiencia será la próxima semana.
No need. Your hearing's been moved up to next week.
What? Why?
¿Qué? ¿Por qué?
Dígale a su esposo que detesto las amenazas.
You tell your husband I don't take well to threats.
Right.
Claro. Prefiere los sobornos, ¿verdad?
You much prefer bribes, don't you?
Tiene salsa en la corbata, Karl.
You got some sauce on your tie, Karl.
Read 'em and weep, boys.
Pónganse a llorar, muchachos.
- Goddamn. - Yeah!
"State Trooper"]
a clear conscience...
¿Les trampeaste sus salarios a esos muchachos?
You cheat these guys out of their paychecks?
Oh, hey, Royal.
Hola, Royal.
Hola.
Hey, yourself.
¿Puedo sentarme?
Mind if I sit down?
Claro.
Sure.
How about five-card?
¿Jugamos cinco cartas?
Yo reparto.
I'll deal.
What's your ante? Ten? 20?
¿Cuánto apuestas? ¿10, 20?
- Es lo que quieras... - Que sean 20.
- Oh, it's whatever you... - Let's do 20.
Feeling lucky or something?
¿Te sientes afortunado?
Sí, siento algo.
I'm feeling something.
Before we start, though, you mind showing me your feet?
Antes de comenzar,
¿podrías mostrarme los pies?
¿Qué?
- What? - Your feet.
Tus pies. Tienes que mostrarme los pies. Es una costumbre aquí.
You got to show me your feet. It's a custom around here.
¿De qué carajo hablas?
What the fuck are you talking about?
Hace un tiempo, unos chicos jugaban cartas
Well, while back, some guys were playing cards.
y estaban sentados en una mesa como esta,
They were sitting at a table just like this,
in a place not too far from here,
en un lugar cerca de aquí, en una noche oscura y...
in some dark kind of night and...
¡bam!
bang.
Alguien entra por la puerta.
What-something comes knocking through the door
Un hombre alto, pálido, con un largo abrigo dijo que quería jugar.
was a tall pale man in a long coat,
says he wants to play.
El hombre pálido se sentó a la mesa, jugaron unas manos,
Tall pale man sits down at the table,
and they get into a couple three-hands
and one of them drops a card on the floor.
y alguien dejó caer una carta al piso.
Guy grabs a lantern,
El sujeto tomó una linterna para recogerla
goes to pick it up, shines the lantern under the table
y alumbró debajo de la mesa, ¿y sabes qué vio?
and you know what he sees?
Los pies del hombre pálido eran cascos.
The pale man's feet are hooves.
En ese momento supieron que jugaban con el diablo.
They knew right then they were playing with the devil.
Agarró la carta y miró hacia arriba.
He grabbed the card, looked back up.
El diablo se había ido.
Devil was gone.
You're the tall pale one, buddy.
Tú eres el alto y pálido, amigo.
Why don't you show me yours?
Muéstrame los tuyos.
No, yo estoy bien.
Nah, I'm square.
¿Tienes sed? Creo que necesitas una cerveza.
You thirsty?
You look like you need a beer.
- Sí, quiero una. - Danos unas cervezas.
Yeah, I want a beer. Yeah.
Can we get a couple of beers?
Y un whisky.
- And a whiskey. - Christ.
Dios mío, eres todo un cliché, Royal.
You're like a walking cliché, Royal.
¿También quieres un paquete de Marlboros?
You want a pack of Marlboros, too?
Aw, you're still angry, aren't you?
Sigues enojado, ¿verdad?
Creía que habíamos dicho que era algo del pasado.
I thought we said all that was water under the bridge.
Royal Abbott está molesto porque lo empujé y cayó a un hoyo.
Everyone, Royal Abbott is angry
because I pushed him into a goddamn hole.
Now, ain't that some schoolyard shit?
Eso sí que son boberías de colegiales.
I'm sorry...
Lo lamento.
Juguemos.
Let's play.
¿Por qué jugamos?
What are we playing for?
Para quedarme en tus tierras para siempre.
How about you let me stay on your land forever?
What?
Está bien.
All right.
Si pierdo, te quedas el tiempo que quieras.
I lose, you get to stay as long as you want.
Si pierdes, me cuentas todo de la roca que tienes en el cuello.
You lose, I get the whole story
behind that rock around your neck.
Fine.
Está bien.
You want to up it?
¿Quieres subir?
Sí, quiero subirla.
Yeah, I want to up it.
How about the thing itself?
¿Y si me das esa cosa?
I want that doodad around your neck.
Quiero el adorno de tu cuello.
¿Qué quieres con mi collar?
What do you want with my necklace?
Creo que lo mismo que tú.
Well, I'm guessing same as you.
Quizá es como has dicho.
Maybe it's like you've been saying.
"Algo pasa aquí".
Something's been happening around here.
Something more than we can know.
"Algo más de lo que podemos saber".
¿Qué dices?
So what do you say?
Te diré qué haremos.
I tell you what.
Apuestas la roca de tu cuello, y yo apuesto mis pastizales.
You put up that rock around your neck
and I'll put up my west pasture.
- ¿Qué? - Ya me oíste.
- What? - You heard me.
¿Todos tus pastizales occidentales?
Your entire west pasture?
Las 485 hectáreas.
All 1,200 acres.
¿Hablas en serio?
Are you serious?
Apuestas la roca,
You wager that rock...
y yo apuesto toda la tierra a la que pareces tenerle tanto cariño.
and I'll put up all that land you seem to be so fond of.
De acuerdo.
All right.
Gunsmoke starring James Arness
as Matt Dillon.
Oh, goddamn it!
¡Maldita sea!
¡Carey!
Hey!
¡Vamos, hijo de perra, muéstrame algo!
Come on, motherfucker, show me something!
I'm gonna find you.
No más juegos.
Come on, motherfucker!
¡Vamos, hijo de puta, muéstrame algo!
Show me something!
Sí.
Vaya, vaya.
Oh, me, oh, my.
¿Quién podrías ser?
Who could you be?
Te tengo.
I got you. No!
¿A dónde vas? No, no lo hagas...
Where you headed? No, do not!
www.TUSUBTITULO.com -DIFUNDE LA CULTURA-
Subtítulos: Hernando Durán
Supervisión creativa Rebeca Rambal